Finding Aid for J. David Singer papers, 1947-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Grant Proposals 1958-1997
  - National Science Foundation
    - 1971-1972 (Box 16)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 16)
    - 1975-1982 (Box 16)
    - 1984 (Box 16)
    - 1986 (Box 16)
    - 1992 (Box 16)
  - Phoenix Project
    - 1958-1968 (Box 17)
    - 1978 (Box 17)
    - 1981 (Box 17)
    - 1988 (Box 17)
    - 1990 (Box 17)
  - Rackham Faculty Research 1980-1981 (Box 17)
  - Research Proposal Evaluations and Manuscripts
    - 1961-1999, 12 folders (Box 17)
    - General Files, 4 folders (Box 17)
  - United States Institute of Peace 1988 (Box 17)
  - World Society Foundation 1986-1992 (Box 17)
- Teaching 1959-2004
  The Teaching Series, approximately .5 linear feet, contains syllabi, exam questions, and some anonymous course evaluations of the numerous classes that Professor Singer has taught at the University of Michigan. Also included is a folder concerning a class given at National Chengchi University in Taiwan.
  - National Chengchi University, Department of Diplomacy, International Security in the Global System 1998 (Box 18)
  - PS 160, Introduction to World Politics 1971 (Box 18)
  - PS 167, Foreign Policies of the European Powers 1959-1960 (Box 18)
  - PS 266, Proseminar in International Relations 1958-1960 (Box 18)
  - PS 361, Current Issues in World Politics 1983 (Box 18)
  - PS 450 1990 (Box 18)
  - PS 460, Problems in World Politics (Box 18)
  - PS 471, United States Foreign Policy 1979-1999 (Box 18)
  - PS 472, International Security Affairs 1968-1969 (Box 18)
  - PS 489, The Global System (Box 18)
  - PS 498, The Global System; War and the Environment: A Lethal Reciprocity; War in World Politics; From War to War; Unconventional Foreign Policies; Intelligence and Foreign Policy Prediction; The Soviet Union and the World Economy 1990-2004 (Box 18)
  - PS 498, Intelligence and Prediction in Foreign Policy 2002 (Box 18)
  - PS 600, Proseminar in World Politics (Box 18)
  - PS 661, Theory Building in World Politics 1965-1993 (Box 18)
  - PS 661, Coursepack (Box 18)
  - PS 662, System and Behavior in World Politics: Toward an Interdisciplinary Science 1966-1979 (Box 18)
  - PS 664, Research Strategy and Methods in International Relations 1966-1999 (Box 18)
  - PS 667, Analysis and Prediction in Comparative Foreign Policy 1975-1989 (Box 18)
  - PS 668, War in World Politics 1971-2001 (Box 18)
  - PS 671, United States Foreign Policy in the Global Complex 1997-1999 (Box 18)
  - PS 672, Proseminar in International Peace and Security 1986 (Box 18)
  - PS 768, Research Seminar on Conflict Systems 2002 (Box 18)
- Programs 1972-1989
  The Programs series (1972-1989), approximately 3 linear feet, contains information on the Law and World Politics and Peace research programs, and include proposals for research.
  There is extensive information regarding the Correlates of War Project, also known as COW. Extant are correspondence which provides an excellent snapshot of the daily operation of the project and discussions regarding the selection and presentation of data. Although the COW, Staff Meeting Notes (1971-1975) are somewhat cryptic, those already familiar with the project will find these notes helpful in understanding the resolution of various methodological problems in the research. There are also hard-copy printouts of data sets.
  - Correlates of War
    - A Brief History (Box 18)
    - Bibliographies 1982-2001 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence
      - 1967-1968 (Box 18)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 18)
      - 2001 (Box 18)
      - 2004-2006 (Box 18)
    - Data
      - Coders' User Manuals (Box 18)
      - Correspondence Regarding Data 1967-1986 (Box 18)
      - Descriptors (Box 18)
      - Findings (Box 18)
      - Miscellaneous Data Sets, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - War Data Sets, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - War Typology (Box 19)
    - Database Acquisition (Box 19)
    - Douglas M. Gibler Publications (Box 19)
    - Drafts 1976 (Box 19)
    - Future of War Workshop 2001 (Box 19)
    - ICPSR Codebook (Box 19)
    - ICPSR, "Wages of War, 1816-1980" (Box 19)
    - Internet Sites, Printouts 1996-2007 (Box 19)
    - Interim Report and Rationale 1972 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Newsletter undated (Box 19)
    - Research Descriptions, Annual Reports 1962-1994 (Box 19)
    - Research Design, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Staff Meeting Notes 1971-1975 (Box 19)
    - Staff Rosters 1983-2004 (Box 19)
    - Analyses 1966-1981, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Indicator papers 1970-1986 (Box 23)
    - Research proposals 1975, 1988, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Data Development for International Research, DDIR
    - Correspondence (Box 19)
    - National Science Foundation Grant, Proposals, Ephemera (Box 20)
    - Update Newsletter 1986-1990 (Box 20)
  - Faculty Research Seminar on Arms Control 1961-1964 (Box 20)
  - Law and World Politics 1975-1989, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Peace Research 1972-1989, 4 folders (Box 20)
- Later Materials
  Papers received after Professor Singer’s death comprise the Later Materials series. Most of this includes e-mail communications, files relating to various proposed publications, unpublished manuscripts and miscellaneous departmental communications.
  - Miscellaneous e-mails, reviews, and later teaching activities, 2000-2009, 7 folders (Box 20)
  - Regarding publications
    - Oxford Encyclopedia of Peace (Box 20)
    - International Encyclopedia of Peace (Box 20)
    - Sage handbook of Conflict Resolution (Box 20)
    - Wages of War (Box 20)
  - Earlier materials 1960s-1990s (Box 20)
  - "Empirical knowledge on world politics: summaries of data-based research, 1970-1988," 1990 1960s-1990s (Box 20)
  - Unpublished manuscripts
    - "The correlates, causes, and consequences of war, 1816-1975," 1975 (Box 20)
    - "Crowding and combat in animal and human societies: the European nations, 1816-1965," 1971 (Box 20)
    - "Random thoughts on projected needs of the international politics field," 1967 (Box 20)
    - "Ecological and behavioral correlates of modern international war," 1971 (Box 20)
    - "War, peace, and global governance," 1996 (Box 20)
    - "The management of serious international disputes: historical patterns since the Congress of Vienna," 1979 (Box 20)
    - "Capabilities, allocations, and conflict avoidance among major powers, 1816-1976: a research note," 1987 (Box 20)
    - "Armed conflict in the ex-colonial regions: from classification to explanation," 1994 (Box 20)
    - "Papers by others," 1985, 1988-1989 (Box 20)
- Audio Visual Materials
  The Audio Visual series, 1 linear ft, contains audio tapes of political science lectures given by Professor Singer and others. Also included are VHS tapes, two DVDs and a CD-ROM of lectures, interviews and special programs.
  - Audio Tapes
    - "J. David Singer, Department of Political Science", 1 audiocassettes (Box 21)
    - PS 160 Lectures, 5 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; 3 3/4 ips
      - January 14, 1971 January 19, 1971 (Box 21)
      - January 21, 1971 January 26, 1971 (Box 21)
      - February 11, 1971, April 13, 1971 (Anatol? Rapoport guest lecturer) (Box 21)
        (side one poor recording quality)
      - February 16, 1971 April 15, 1971 (Box 21)
      - April, 1975 Kathy Kelleher and Ken Organski (Box 21)
    - Lecture on world politics undated, 1 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes (Box 21)
    - Lecture on global terrorism at the University of Michigan International Center October 10, 1972 and untitled lecture at Temple University, undated, 1 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes (Box 21)
    - Untitled and unidentified, 5 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes (Box 21)
  - Digital materials
    - COW seminar, the University of Michigan, 2006, 1 optical disks CD-RWs (Box 21)
    - Honorary Degree presentation at the SUNY Commencement, 2007, 1 optical disks DVD-Rs (Box 21)
    - Video conference with students, undated, 1 optical disks DVD-ROMs (Box 21)
  - Videotapes
    - "Peace In Our Time," Alumni University July, 1993, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 21)
    - "Peace Research and the Current World Scene," Alumni University August 12, 1991, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 21)
    - "War and Peace in the Global Village," Alumni University June 26, 1989, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 21)
    - "War and Peace Seminar," (Moore and Turner), University of Virginia Law School February, 1999, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 21)
    - "War on Terror Film Project," Winter 2002, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 21)